你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎收看PWN学院的视频
welcome to another video on pwn college
本片主要讲权限提升
this one is on privilege escalation
我们先介绍一下，再深入
all right let's introduce privilege escalation and dive in
之后演示三个习题
and then send you along to try your hand at the practice problems
好的，回想一下Linux权限模型
all right so recall the Linux permission model
我说“回想”
and i say recall
是因为我假设，在这个模块以及这门课中
because i assume in this module and in this course
你已经对Linux权限模型有所了解
that you have an understanding of the Linux permission model already
至少是从使用者的角度
from a user's perspective
如果不知道
if you don't
若有足够的需求
if there's enough demand
我们可能出一期Linux权限模型的基础视频
we might create a fundamentals video about the Linux permission model
但这里，我就浅浅的讲一下
but here i'm just gonna talk about a very high level in Linux
希望这是个复习
hopefully this is review
每个进程都有一个uid和一个gid
every process has a user id and a group id
这是个终端的截图
so here as a screenshot of my terminal
我执行了id命令
i ran the id command
打印出了uid，为1000
id printed out its user id which is 1000
当然，对内核来说，它们只是数字
of course to the kernel they're all numbers
但这些uid数字，有对应的名字
but these numeric user ids have names associated with them
这样方便人用
so that they're more approachable by humans
我还有个gid，也是1000
and i have a group id of also 1000
这些是Ubuntu中默认的主要用户的id
these are the default primary user ids on Ubuntu
我们这里不讨论groups（附加组）
all right we won't talk about the secondary groups i have
之后你可以自行研究
you might dig into that in a later time
重要的是每个用户都有一个uid和gid
but essentially every user has a user id and a group id
Linux中每个文件和目录都归属于一个组中用户
and every file and every directory in Linux is owned by a user in a group
我这里看了一下/bin/cat
so here i look at /bin/cat
/bin/cat属于root
and i see that /bin/cat is owned by root
也属于root组
and has a group owner of root as well
它属于root组和root用户
so the root group and the root user
在左边，你能看到它的权限
and on the left you see its permissions
重要的是：rwx
and the relevant thing here is rwx
接着 rx 和 rx
and then r x and then r x
或者说 r-x 和 r-x
or r-x and r-x
它代表着什么
and what this means
第一个rwx是针对用户的
the first rwx is for the user
所以，它的拥有者root
so the root user that's who owns it
可以读、写和执行这个文件
can read write and execute this file
root组的可以读和执行这个文件
the root group can read and execute this file
所以在root组的所有进程
so any process that is in the root group
我说“进程”，而不是用户
and i said process not user
是因为实际被检查权限的是进程
because it's the process on which these permissions are checked
当然，创建一个进程时
but of course when you create a process
或者说登录账号创建初始会话时
or when you create your initial session as a user
进程初始化时会收到这些权限（应该是说euid）
your initial process receives these permissions as it set up
然后不在root组中的其余用户，也可以读和执行
and then anyone not in the root group the rest of the world can also read and execute
我一直说权限
i keep mentioning you know permissions
这些凭据存在于进程级别
these credentials exist on the process level
一般来说，子进程从父进程继承它们
child processes inherit them from their parent generally speaking
有一些特殊的情况是不同的
there're exotic situations that are different
但一般来说，父进程会设置一些
but generally speaking the parent will set up some
实际上马上会讲一种特殊情况
and actually one of the exotic situations will go into right now
但一般来说
but generally speaking the
父进程启动子进程，而子进程
parent runs the child and child
回忆一下基础模块中的进程加载
if you recall from the fundamental series on Linux process loading
父进程执行fork时
when the parent forks
子进程会继承父进程的所有，包括凭据
the child will inherit everything that the parent has in terms of credentials
也有例外
there are exceptions
这里又有一个终端的截图
so here i have on my terminal again a screenshot
我写了个程序叫getuid，只调用了getuid
i created a getuid program that just calls getuid
这个系统调用
it is a system call that
好吧，这是个c函数
well this is a C function
它最终会调用系统调用，获得我的uid
that eventually calls a system call that gets me my user id
我执行了它
i executed it
当然此时的用户id还是1000，我执行了它
and of course here i still have my 1000 user and then i run it
输出1000
and it also says 1000
好吧
all right um
有1000之外的uid
there are user ids other than 1000
比如，0
one very specific one is 0
在Linux和其他类unix系统上
on Linux and other unix like systems
uid 0是特殊的
user id 0 is special
它表示root
that is root
它是系统管理员用户
it's the system administrator user
它用于
it's used for
你必须是root才能对系统做大的修改
you need to be root for making large system changes
安装软件
installing software
修改大多数的系统范围的配置
and most configurations system wide at least
加载设备驱动
loading device drivers
修改系统状态和设置，等等
changing the system state and settings and so forth
如果你的uid是1000或1001
and so if you are user id 1000 or 1001 or whatever other one
你该如何成为uid 0
how do you become user id 0
好吧，我们开始深入
well let's dig in
要想提升权限，成为uid 0
so you become user id zero by elevating your privileges
可以通过利用setuid的程序
by using for example a setuid binary
最有名的
the most famous example of this
也是现在最常见的，是sudo
the most common one nowadays is sudo right
右上角有个关于它的流行的xkcd漫画
so there's a popular xkcd comic about it on the top right there
尝试运行某个命令
you try to run a command
没有权限
you don't have the permission
执行sudo 接上那个命令
do sudo that command
然后你就有权限了
and then you have the permissions
大概你最常用sudo的时候是
the most common thing that you probably sudo for
用apt安装软件
is apt to install software
我最开始接触Linux时
back when i first started using Linux
我们不用sudo
we didn't really use sudo
大多数人使用su
most people used su
功能很类似
very similar sort of conceptual functionality
至少和大多数人用到的sudo的功能很类似
that at least to what most people use sudo for
基本上
basically
是的，非常相似
yeah very similar
就是要root的密码
just required the root users to have its own password
那么sudo、su
all right how does sudo and su
还有newgrp，它能让你切换到
and things like newgrp which actually allows you to swap into
之前看到的附加组中的某一组
one of those secondary groups that you saw on my profile on my user id and so forth
它们用了什么原理
how does this work
它们用了linux权限模型中的额外位
well they work using additional bits in the Linux permission model
我们讲文件权限模型时，没讲它们
that file permission model that we didn't talk about
我们讨论了所属用户的读、写、执行
we talked about the user read write execute
所属组内的读、写、执行
the group read write execute
和其它用户的读、写、执行
and the world read write execute
但还有3位没说
but there are three more bits that we haven't discussed
其中最重要的是setuid位
the most important of these is the SetUID bit
紧接着setgid位
followed by the SetGID bit
如果设置了这些位
if these bits are set
那么有效id
then the effective
等一下，我需要解决一件事
hold on i need to fix one thing
好吧，我不知道为什么没有更新
all right i'm not sure why that didn't update
但它现在改好了
but it is there now
当你运行一个文件
so when you run a file
执行一个文件时
when you execute a file
并且它设置了setuid位
and it has the SetUID bit set
进程的euid
the process executes with an effective user id
稍后会讨论euid的含义
and we'll talk about what this means
会是文件的所有者，而不是父进程的euid
of the file owner rather than the parent process
gid也一样
same with the group id
如果执行了一个设置了setgid位的文件
if you have the SetGID bit set and you execute a file
那么进程的egid是文件个gid
then the resulting process will have the group id of the file
而不是父进程的egid
rather than of the parent process
还有第三位，粘滞位
there's the third bit the sticky bit
它在相对于所属用户和组的其它
that's you know the world equivalent of the user and group
它是完全不同的
it's completely different
它用于目录
it's used on directories
如果你有一个可供多个用户写的共享目录
if you have a shared directory that's writable by multiple users
粘滞位可以保证
then the sticky bit will ensure that
用户只能删除自己添加的文件
a user can only remove files that they have added
他们不能删除别人的文件
they can't remove other people's files
完全不同
completely separate
但也是权限模型的一部分
but also part of this permission model
通常用于/tmp目录
usually used for /tmp directories
或者作业目录之类的东西
or homework directories or something along these lines
我刚刚说了euid
i mentioned the effective user id
什么是euid
so what is the euid
我在第一次直播中做了简化
it turns out that i simplified things in the first live
每个进程实际有三类uid或gid
so every process has actually three types of user and group ids
有效id、实际id和保存id
effective real and saved
有效用户id（euid）是用来
the effective user id is what is used for
找不到一个更好的词
lack of a better different term
更不起冲突的词
less colliding term
euid用于访问控制检查
the effective user id is used for access control checks
打开文件时
so when you try to open a file
会检查你的euid
it checks okay what is your effective id
实际id基本表示进程的真实身份
the real id is basically the the true identity of the process
例如，尝试发信号时
for example if you are trying to send signals to a process
检查的就是它
that is what will be checked
保存的id用于
the saved id is used for
如果你是一个特权进程
if you are a privileged process
你为了更安全，想执行些非特权操作
and you want to perform some action unprivileged for extra safety
你可以保存你的特权uid
you can save your privileged user id
假设成一个非特权进程的euid与实际id
assume an effective and real id of a non privileged process
等不需要降低特权时，再用保存id恢复特权
and then restore from your saved user id when you're done needing to lower your privileges
这实际上会导致安全漏洞
this usually actually leads to security vulnerabilities
不管你在以非特权方式做什么
if you're unprivileged whatever you're doing in an unprivileged way
它都会访问保存的uid
it gets access to that saved user id and
因为这就是系统的运作方式
because this is how the system works
保存uid的意义
the whole point of that save user id
就是能重置euid
is to be able to reset your effective user id
然后还能重新提升权限
then they can reelevate their privileges
这不是很重要
this isn't quite as important
过于深入了
i probably went way deeper into it than necessary
重点是euid
the point is that effective user id
setuid位的作用是什么呢
and what happens when you have a SetUID bit
它会修改euid吗
is it sets that effective user id
我们来看看
so let's take a look
好吧
all right
这是getuid.c
so i have my getuid.c
还有一个getgid.c
i also have a getgid.c
cat拼错了
wrong cat
好
okay cool
编译它们
let's compile them
关闭警告
turn off warnings
因为我没include
because i didn't add any includes
这样ppt上占地能小点
so these are smaller for the slides
好的
awesome
我们运行getuid
so let's run getuid
输出uid 1000
says user 1000
执行getgid，输出gid 1000
getgid group 1000
当然，这是我的用户和组
of course that's my user and my group
我们看一下getgid和getuid
let's take a look at getgid and uid
对于用户yans，它们都是可读可写可执行的
they are readable writeable executable by user yans
对于用户yans（口误），也是可读可写可执行
readable writeable and executable by user(group) yans
可读和可执行
readable and executable by
抱歉，第二个是yans组
sorry the second one was group yans
对于非yans组的，只是可读可执行
and readable and executable by not group yans
任何非yans用户，或不在yans组的
anyone that is not user yans or group yans
就是说系统上的其他用户
so other users on the system
我希望这个系统上没有其他用户
i hope there are no other users on this system
因为那对我来说将是个惊吓
because that would be a surprise to me
我们加上setuid位
so let's add the setuid bit
我们用这种语义方法
we're gonna use these sort of semantic meaning
你也该认识这个
you should also know what this means
现在这会把setuid位加到用户这部分
but right now this will add the setuid bit to the user part of this
太棒了
awesome
运行getuid
let's run getuid
好吧，看看
all right let's take a look
好的
all right
现在它是个特殊的二进制程序
so now this is a special binary
它能执行
it will run
我还拥有对它的执行权限
i still have execute permissions to it
你得相信我说的
you have to take my word for it
我没有移除它的可执行权限
i didn't remove them
这只表示在用户部分加了setuid位
all this says is to the user permissions add the setuid
如果没有可执行权限，setuid是无用的
setuid is kind of useless without executable permissions
因为你要执行文件
because you have to execute the file
目前用户能读、写、执行加setuid位
so i have read write and execute with the setuid as user
组能读、写、执行
still read write and execute as group
其它用户能读、执行
read execute as the world
如果我执行它
and if i execute it
我会显示为root吗
will i be root
不会
no
有两个原因
there are two reasons
我们稍后讨论第二个原因
we'll get into the second one later
第一个原因是文件所有者是yans
the first one is that the owner is yans
所以euid要被设为的，是yans
so the id that i'm assuming that i'm becoming the effective user id is yans
第二个原因是
the second one
我们先解决第一个问题
so let's actually fix that first one
让它归root所有
let's make this owned by root
现在我们来看一看
now let's take a look
能看到设置的setuid位消失了
one thing you'll notice that happened is the setuid bit is gone
这是一种安全措施
this is a security precaution
当你改变，或者说用chown后
when you change you or at least when you use chown
我不确定用chown系统调用，会不会这样
i'm not sure if you use the chown syscall this will happen
用chown修改文件归属后
when you use chown to change ownership of a file
会重置setuid位
it'll also reset the setuid bit
好吧
all right
所以
so
我们重新设置好
let's set it back over there all right
好的
cool
现在我们有了个root的文件
now we have a file owned by root
并且设置了setuid位
that has setuid in the user
如果我执行这个
so if i run this
我应该是root，对吧
i should be root right
错。为什么？
wrong why
其实很简单
well it's very simple
我用的这个getuid函数
getuid this function i'm using
它会获取实际uid
it gets the real user id
如果执行geteuid
if you do geteuid
才会获得euid
that'll get me the effective user id
okay了
and then will be good to go
编译它
so i compile it
又成yans的文件了
okay here it is again owned by me
chown改下
let's chown it
好的，chmod改下
awesome chmod it
我们看一下
let's take a look okay
执行getuid。euid 为 0
run getuid effective user id zero
那egid呢
what about my effective group id
与其费时间说它是怎样的
so rather than spend time showing you that it's the real okay
我们直接看例子
let's just look straight at the effective one
这是getgid
so here is getgid
chown改一下
you're gonna chown
好了
there we go
没权限，就sudo
operation not permitted sudo boom
好的
okay
我在用户部分加上了setuid位
now i chmod it user setuid
目前setuid位加在了用户部分
or setuid which is on the user
那么yans执行它会是什么情况
so what will this run as group wides
egid还是1000
well group wides the effective group id should still be 1000
因为不会用文件gid修改进程egid
because there's nothing that'll change it
没设置setgid位
the setgid isn't there
是的
yep
那么如果我们设置gid呢
so what if we set the group gid
我们来看一看
let's take a look
设置好了
now it's set very cool
运行，是0
run it zero
好的
okay awesome
我展示了setuid和setgid是有用的
i've shown to you that setuid and setgid work
还有一件事
one thing by the way
让我们
let's
这是重置它们的一个简单方法
just that was an easy way to reset them
ls查看一下
get you ls to get uid and gid cool
都重置了
it's all reset
现在执行sudo ./getgid
now i'm gonna do sudo ./getgid
用sudo，会启动一个新会话
one thing that to give my sudo will start a new session
新会话的用户是sudo的目标用户，通常是root
as whatever user you're sudo into usually root
一般来说，它会设置好需要的有效id、实际id、保存id
and it'll properly set the effective real saved everything you need generally speak
除非有bug
unless there are bugs
这也时有发生
which happen all right
我们继续
let's roll on
所以
so
你可以成为uid 0
you can become user id 0
但是，权力越大，责任越大
but with great power comes great responsibility
root很强大
root is extremely powerful
除了能更改你的系统
aside from making changes on your system
你还能打开或删除任意文件
you can open any file or remove any file
可以违反所有的文件权限
or actually violate file permissions altogether
我们稍后讨论为什么这样
we'll talk later about why this occurs
其中包括了特殊的/proc
this includes the special /proc file system
作为root你能，比如，读取任意进程的内存
so as root you can for example read the memory of any process
因为内存中有个特殊的文件
because there's a special file in the memory
/proc/self/mem
so you can do /proc/self/mem
你能打开这个特殊文件
this is a special file that you can open
通过它读出虚拟内存中的数据
and read out the memory contents in virtual memory of this file
这是一件很严肃的事情
that's you know pretty serious thing
同样，它也可以写入数据
it can also by the way write these memory content
所以root基本上能做任何事
so root can already do basically anything
哦
oops
我切到终端，展示一下，这是那个文件
let me jump to the terminal to show you here is that file
里面是内存中的内容
there's the memory of your content
这对你的进程的内存来说，是个坏消息
pretty bad news for the memory of your process
实际上，如果你看一下/proc
and actually if you look at /proc
这是我系统上运行的所有进程
this is all of the different processes running on my system
root可以获取任意一个进程的内存
and root could grab the memory of any of them all right
你可以更改配置改变这个情况
there are things you can do to change this configuration
但我们讨论的是最常见的情况
but we're talking about most common cases
root用户可以执行任何程序
root can execute any program
假设成任意的uid、gid
assume any other user group id
调试任意程序
debug any program
将调试器附加到任意程序
attached to programs with debuggers etc
这是常规情况
again in in normally
有方法可以改变这个状况
there are ways to change this
但正常情况下
but obviously in the normal case
这是一场安全灾难
this is a security disaster right
你不想任何
you really don't want anyone to
不该有root权限的用户成为root
that is not supposed to be root to be root
但人们总是想成为root
but people try to become root all the time
漏洞利用中的这一步，或一类漏洞称为提权
this step of an exploit or class of vulnerability is called a privilege escalation
在提权时
in a privilege escalation exploit
攻击者，通常已经在系统中获得立足点
an attacker generally after gaining a foothold on the system
不管是利用有漏洞的网络服务
whether through a vulnerable network service
或者他们找到了能访问的shell
or maybe they have intended shell access
比如，在课堂自动评分系统中
so for example in a class auto grading system
或者攻击者可以控制你设备上应用程序中的一些代码
or maybe the attacker can control some code in an app on your device
比如，这个应用就在你的手机中
but the app is running on your phone for example
它运行在一个非常受限的环境中
right it's running in a very constrained environment
下一步通常是找到
the next step is usually to identify
该设备中有漏洞的特权进程
some sort of vulnerable privilege process on that device
或者是在作业评分的服务器中找
or on the shared homework grading server
或者你在的什么设备上
or wherever you are
利用它，获取它的权限
exploit that to gain his privileges right
一个常见的攻击面是setuid程序
a good a common attack surface for this is a setuid binary
有程序带有setuid或setgid位
so there's something running with as setuid or setgid or something
且它有漏洞
and it is vulnerable
这在课程评分系统中很常见
very frequently happens for course grading systems
攻击者可以利用它
attackers can use it
获得特权
exploit it to gain its privileges
这有点像一个高地
it's kind of like a highlander thing
两个程序为此争斗，只有一个获得它
two programs will fight and there can only be one
可能这是一个非常过时的描述
probably that's a very outdated reference
不管怎样，我们继续
anyways let's move on
会有人这么粗心
so would anyone be careless enough
给有漏洞的程序设置setuid位吗
to have vulnerable setuid programs thing at all
事实证明，是的
it turns out absolutely
我刚刚说的sudo，无处不在
i mean we just talking about sudo installed everywhere
所以setuid无处不在
setuid everywhere
往回看
if you go back
每一年，谷歌下一页都点烦了
every single year until i got bored googling back in time
sudo都有高危漏洞
sudo has had serious critical vulnerabilities
这能让攻击者
that would allow attackers to
在很多不同配置或情况，提权
acquire elevated privileges in many different configurations and use cases
这很可怕，因为sudo无处不在
which is very scary because sudo is everywhere
sudo有漏洞
so sudo is vulnerable
其他不太常见的很少被关注的setuid程序
it's very likely that other less common setuid programs and thus less looked at
很可能也有漏洞
are vulnerable as well
另一个，我们提到的课程自动评分系统
i mean another we mentioned the course auto grading system
另一个大的攻击面是
another large attack surface is
没必要但被sudo
programs that are unnecessarily either sudoed
我想说的是，但被设置了setuid的程序
or setuid is what i meant to type on this slide
或者通过其他方式以root执行的
or run as root by some other means
这很常见
this is very common
就像我刚说的课程评分系统
like i said in course grading systems
以及共享服务器管理软件
and shared server management software
我还在业界的时候
when i was in industry
我经常看到这种情况
i saw this quite a lot
它也变得越来越普遍
it is also increasingly becoming common
随着容器化以及docker的兴起
with the rise of containerization and docker
有很多docker容器
there's a lot of docker containers
就以root用户执行所有东西
that unnecessarily run everything as root
因为他们能，和方便
because they can and it's easier
这打开了些攻击面
this opens up some level of attack surface
虽然docker容器通常被隔离了
even though a docker container is generally contained
但这是一些额外的访问途径
but it is some additional access
攻击者不一定非要能获得它
that is not strictly necessary for an attacker to be able to acquire
另一种非常常见的提权方法
another very common way to do privilege escalation
是通过操作系统级，内核级漏洞
is through OS level kernel level vulnerabilities
我们将在几个月后讨论这个问题
we'll be talking about this in a several months
请继续关注
so stay tuned on that
好的
all right so
这个模块的介绍视频到此结束
this brings us to the end of this introductory video for this module
我们接下来讨论习题
and we will talk about the practice problems
我会现场做几个
now i'll actually do a few live
这个模块有一些
so this module has several
准确的说是有100个习题
specifically one hundred practice problems
你必须解决100个习题才能得到满分
or rather you have to solve one hundred practice problems to get full points
一般来说，我们会连接到pwn.college
generally speaking we're going to connect to pwn college
选一个习题
we're going to select one of the 100 instances of practice problem
每个都要求我们
each one will let us
输入一个linux程序的路径
input a program path of like a Linux utility
该程序会被设置setuid位
that utility will just be granted setuid access
或会检查setuid位
or the setuid bit will be checked
你要用这个工具来读取/flag
and you have to use that utility to read /flag
它只有root用户可读
which is only readable by root
所以你要用它提权
so you have to use that to either escalate your privileges
或者直接读文件
or just read the file all right
我们要演示第三个
we're gonna demo three
这些解题方法都可以用
these are free solutions for you if you want to use them
如果你不想用它们，想要更大的挑战
if you don't want to use them and want a bigger challenge
就别用，换种方法
don't use them do something else
我展示一下
let me show you
我们开始吧
so let's start all right
好的
okay
这是我们的网站
here is the website
pwn.college 的首页
the front page of pwn college
如果刷新一下
if you refresh it
稍等
hold on
我电脑出问题了
my computer's having issues okay
问题解决了
issue solved
好的，如果你点击模块一
all right if you click through module one
就是这个模块
so here is the module
这是到该视频的链接
here's a link to this video
这些是你可能想知道的Linux基础系列视频
these are fundamentals that you might want to know
如果我们做了Linux进程权限相关的基础视频
if we end up creating fundamentals of Linux process permissions
或Linux权限模型的
or the Linux permission model
我会把它加在这里
i'll add that there
还有一些其它解题思路的描述
and some descriptions involving other free solutions
如果你感兴趣的话
if you're interested
我们点击它，看看习题
so let's click through to get to the challenges
我已经登录了
i'm already logged in
来到习题页面
you go to the challenges
这有100个习题
here are the 100 instances
点击习题1
so you click on instance 1
我已经解决了这个 cat
i've already solved cat
我马上告诉你怎么做
but i'm just going to show you how to do it
这里输入/bin/cat
here we do /bin/cat
运行它
run it
哦，多了个空格
oh it put a space
要确保路径是正确的
make sure that you have the path correct
运行它
run it
它告诉我可以连接了
alright so it tells me i can connect
我当然可以用SSH登录
i can of course ssh in
但我这里就用web终端
but i'm going to use the terminal on the web page
这更容易
it's easier
能看到/bin/cat设置了setuid，且归属于root
i can see that /bin/cat is now setuid root
我可以查看/flag文件
i can look at /flag
它只有root可读
which is only readable by root
这题很简单
but it's nice and easy
我可以直接用cat输出
because i can cat it out
这个就是flag
and here's the flag
这是我的flag
this is my flag
不要提交我的flag
don't submit my flag
每个人都有自己的flag
everyone gets their own flag
去拿你自己的flag吧
get your own flag all right
这很简单
so that was nice and easy let's
我可以复制这个flag
so i can of course copy this flag
复制
copy
回到习题列表页面
i can go back to the challenges
粘贴flag
paste the flag
不对，这是
nope that's the
粘贴flag，提交
paste the flag submit
我已经解决过这题了
and i already solved cats
所以没提示成功
so it's not gonna let me do it again all right
我们再做几个
so let's do more
我已经解了/bin/cat
so i already solve /bin/cat
我们
let's do
是/bin/more，还是/usr/bin/more
is it /bin/more or /usr/bin/more
我们两种都试试
let's try both
是的
yep
是/bin/more
it is /bin/more
好
awesome
现在来到终端
so you go into the terminal now
看，/bin/more有setuid位，归属于root
see /bin/more is setuid root
我们的flag还在/flag
our flag is still /flag
cat是一个输出程序
so cat was a program that just
你可以在命令行上给它一个文件
you would give it a file on the command line
或者默认情况下，它就将你输入的回显出来
or by default it just echoed whatever you said back to it
我们直接运行cat
let's just run cat
看到了吧
see cool
现在我展示一下，cat /flag是没用的
actually now let me show you that cat flag doesn't work
more类似cat，但它会中断
more is similar but it stops and
它是一个分页的程序
it's a pager application
一次输出一页
gives you one page at a time
没分页
there's no
因为这个flag不够长
the flag isn't long enough for that
所以如果执行more /flag
so if you just do more /flag
我们就能拿到flag
and we get the flag
复制它
copy that
回到习题列表
go back to challenges
很好
nice and easy okay
正确
correct
如果我打开这个
so now if i pull this up
能看到我解决了cat和more
i see i've solved cat and more
这些都是用来读取文件的简单程序
those are easy programs that are designed to read a file
有一些程序不是为读取文件而设计的
so there are some programs that aren't designed to read a file
但你可以诱导他们读取文件
that you can trick into reading files
我再演示一个
but i want to show you one more
我展示一下find
i want to show you find
find不是为读取文件而设计的
find isn't designed to read a file
如何解决/usr/bin/find呢
so how do we solve /usr/bin/find
好的
okay
它上线了
they're alive
我们切到终端
let's go to challenges terminal sorry
看一下/usr/bin/find
and we look at /usr/bin/find
好的，有setuid位
setuid all right
flag依旧是不可读的
our flag as always is unreadable
我们可以执行find /flag
so i can do find /flag
find是做什么的?
what does find do
看一下find --help
well i look at find --help
这至少告诉了我们，它的参数
i mean this at least shows you the arguments
find所做的是，为你查找文件
what find does is find files for you right
你给它一些条件
you give it a bunch of criteria
它会找到他们
and it'll find them
有趣的是
the interesting thing is that
find能做的事情之一
one of the things that find can do
这一点非常重要
and this is very important
因为find不是唯一一个有该功能的
because find is not the only one
就是-exec
is -exec
所以find可以执行命令
so find can execute commands
如果你有个系统能查看man手册
if you have a system where you have man pages
或者直接搜索man find
or if you just go and do man find
打开这个man手册
pull up this man page
仔细阅读-exec的功能
read up on what -exec does
它会执行给定的命令
it executes the command that's given
以及你使用它的方式
and the way that you use it
我才发现这很难看清
that's pretty unreadable in the text i realized
用它的方法是
the way that you use it is
先输入-exec，然后是命令
you give a -exec and then the command
然后是这个花括号
and then this curly braces
如果你读了这个就知道
which are if you read this
它会被找到的文件名替换
will be replaced by the file name
然后是分号
and then a semicolon
它表示命令在此结束
which is where it'll terminate
所以我们
so let's
连接断了
this loss connection
好了，我们回来了
all right we're back
我们可以执行id
so we could execute something like id
我们来试一下
let's try it out
用分号必须要转义
with a semicon has to escape the semicon
否则将终止执行命令
otherwides it'll terminate the command
因为我们在bash中
because we're in bash here
执行吧
so let's do this
路径必须跟着这个
path must proceeds this
我刚才没有正确使用find
so i wasn't using find it correctly just now
/flag放在前面
the find /flag alright
有趣的是
so here's an interesting thing
find执行了id
find executed id
你可以看到
and you can see
是以root的有效用户id运行的
that i am running as euid effective user id of root
这太不可思议了
so this is incredible
到这应该就能解决问题了
at this point we should be done
当然我们能解决
and of course we are
我们可以执行cat
so i can do cat
我给它加一个花括号
and i give it its curly brackets
flag出来了
and here it is
所以刚才发生了什么
so what just happened
它以root身份执行了cat /flag
it executed cat /flag as root
用的是root的euid
with an effective user id of root
所以通过了权限检查
so that permission check passed
可以复制它
can copy this
来到习题列表
can go to the challenges
打开第三题
can go instance 3
粘贴flag
and flag
好了
all right
你现在获得了3分
you now have three additional three freebies
如果你看过pwn.college上的这个模块
if you read the module on pwn college
里面还有几个
there's a couple more in there
我觉得你能拿到100分
i think you can get to a hundred
祝你好运
good luck